Welcome to the Tech Meme Ride Home for Monday, September 30th, 2024. I'm Brian McCullough. Today,
that controversial AI bill in California has been vetoed by Governor Newsom.
Is even Apple now thinking that its Vision Pro strategy might need a rethink? What really is
OpenAI's situation right now, and this time I'm talking money-wise, and the strange resurrection
of the point-and-shoot camera? Here's what you missed today in the world of tech.
California Governor Gavin Newsom has vetoed AI Safety Bill SB 1047, saying it applies only to
large AI models and doesn't account for if deployment is high risk. This was that AI bill
that a lot of the AI community and AI VCs were very worried about, quoting the journal.
California Governor Gavin Newsom has vetoed a controversial artificial intelligence safety
bill that pitted some of the biggest tech companies against prominent scientists who developed the
technology. The Democrat decided to reject the measure because it applies only to the biggest
and most expensive AI models and doesn't take into account whether they are deployed in high-risk
situations, he said in his veto message. Smaller models sometimes handle critical decision-making
involving sensitive data such as electrical grids and medical records, while bigger models at times
handle low-risk activities such as customer service. Had Newsom signed the bill into law, it would have
laid the groundwork for how AI is regulated across the U.S. as California is home to the top companies
in the industry. Proposals to regulate AI nationally have made little progress in Washington.
The governor announced that he is working with leading AI researchers including
Fai Fai Lee, a Stanford University professor who has worked at Google and recently launched a startup
called World Labs to develop new legislation he is willing to support. Newsom signed other AI-related
bills into law this year. They include one requiring AI developers to label content created by their
technology and others regulating election-related deepfakes and giving performers more control over
digital replicas of themselves. The bill he vetoed, SB 1047, would have required developers of large AI
models to take, quote, reasonable care to ensure that their technology didn't pose, end quote,
unreasonable risk of causing or materially enabling a critical harm. It defined that harm as cyberattacks
that cause at least $500 million in damages or mass casualties. Developers also would have needed
to ensure their AI could be shut down by a human if it started behaving dangerously. The bill applied
to AI models that met a certain computing power threshold and cost at least $100 million to train,
the estimated cost of OpenAI's biggest model, GPT-4. Any company doing business in California,
regardless of where it is headquartered, was covered. Google, Meta, Microsoft, and OpenAI raised
concerns about the bill, saying it imposed vague standards in the name of safety. Many smaller
companies joined them, arguing the bill would chill innovation by discouraging large developers from
making their models available to the public, fracturing a startup ecosystem that relies on such openness
to innovate. The bill would have prohibited developers from releasing large AI models, quote,
if there is an unreasonable risk that the technology will cause or materially enable a critical harm.
Tech companies said the language opened a legal minefield. Nobody knows what that means.
So you're basically leaving it to a court that's non-technical, said Martin Casado,
a partner overseeing AI investments at venture capital firm Andreessen Horowitz, end quote.
One more real quick, though, it's not quite related. Governor Newsom also signed the California
Neuro Rights Act into law that treats neural data as personal sensitive information aiming to protect
brain data from misuse, quoting the Times.
On Saturday, Governor Gavin Newsom of California signed a new law that aims to protect people's
brain data from being potentially misused by neurotechnology companies. A growing number of
consumer technology products promise to help address cognitive issues, apps to meditate, to improve focus,
and to treat mental health conditions like depression. These products monitor and record brain data,
which encodes virtually everything that goes on in the mind, including thoughts, feelings,
and intentions. The new law, which passed both the California State Assembly and the Senate with no
voter opposition, amends the state's current personal privacy law known as the California Consumer
Privacy Act by including neural data under personal sensitive information. This includes data generated by a
user's brain activity and the meshwork of nerves that extends to the rest of the body, end quote.
Mark Gurman Newsletter Monday this weekend. Mark took a look at the fallout from the demo
of those meta Orion prototype smart glasses. Mark straight out came out and said, even though it was just a
demo, it made even him think that Apple's strategy with the Vision Pro might be a mistake. Quote,
Apple seems aware that it needs to rethink its approach to headsets, but there isn't consensus
on how to do that, I'm told. As of now, the company's Vision products group is evaluating a
few different options, including the status quo route. This would involve keeping the Vision Pro
more or less the same but focusing on a less expensive version. Apple could bring down the
costs with cheaper materials, lesser internal technologies, and lower quality displays. The company
would also follow up with a second-generation version of the original higher-end Vision Pro that has a
new chip and Apple intelligence. The smart display route. In this scenario, Apple would remove the
onboard computer and external battery from the Vision Pro and shift many of the internal functions
over to the iPhone. This would make the iPhone more valuable, reduce the weight and heat of the headset,
and more importantly, eliminate several hundred dollars worth of components to bring down the price.
Then there's the smart glasses route. This would mean developing a product that's closer to
Meta's hit collaboration with Ray-Ban, smart glasses without AR. Apple could use its expertise in chips
and audio, as well as its growing collection of AI tools to make a compelling device. This would
essentially be a Me Too product, but also something akin to an AirPods on steroids, and Apple fans would
probably eat it up. There's then the AI and AirPods route. Apple is working on a new version of the
AirPods Pro that uses external cameras and artificial intelligence to understand the outside world and
provide information to the user. This would essentially be the smart glasses path, but without actual glasses.
Finally, there's the holy grail route. The ultimate goal is standalone augmented reality spectacles that
come with high-performing lenses, a battery system, onboard computer, cameras, eye tracking, and other
components built in, all while still being the size and weight of normal glasses. This has long been
Chief Executive Officer Tim Cook's dream, but Apple previously paused development of such a product
because it was just too big a challenge. Apple could ultimately release some or all of these products,
but it's going to need to accelerate its work and fast. If not, Apple will risk losing out on a product
category that could transform the way people use technology."
Speaking of Apple, the journal says that Apple is no longer in talks to participate in OpenAI's
funding round that is expected to raise as much as $6.5 billion and close as soon as next week.
Not sure we can or need to make anything out of that particularly right now, but it seems like that
round is coming, which is making people take a hard look at where OpenAI is at the moment financially.
The New York Times has been working their sources and say OpenAI had $300 million in monthly revenue
in August, up 1,700% since early 2023. They had 350 million monthly active users in June and expect
around $3.7 billion in annual sales this year, but also, of course, $5 billion in losses.
Reuters worked their sources to report that OpenAI expects its revenue to grow to $11.6 billion next year.
ChatGPT has 10 million paying users and could bring in $2.7 billion in revenue this year,
up from $700 million in 2023. But again, the question really is, is that growth sustainable if the cost of
providing the product you provide is so expensive? So the journal took a look at the challenges OpenAI is facing
if it indeed becomes a for-profit company, which I guess it needs to do to address all that.
This includes the complexity of splitting assets with the non-profit arm, which, I hadn't thought of this,
might continue to exist. Quoting the journal.
The ChatGPT maker is in the midst of raising $6.5 billion from bankers including Microsoft and NVIDIA,
along with venture capital firms and a United Arab Emirates state-backed company.
An essential provision of talks is that OpenAI, currently governed by a charitable non-profit,
must within two years become a public benefit corporation. That means its mission is to earn
profit while creating social good. If it doesn't, investors could take back their money.
To get there, it will have to deal with regulatory requirements in at least two states,
determine how to award equity in the for-profit company,
and split assets with the non-profit entity, which will continue to exist.
This kind of transaction is incredibly complex and would involve a large number of legal and
regulatory hurdles that would need to be navigated, said Karen Blackenstone,
general counsel at the investment firm Hanger Management and an attorney specializing in
technology and tax-exempt organizations. OpenAI is a Delaware-based corporation and would need to
change its structure legally under that state's law. Given Delaware's business-friendly legal regime,
making that change would be the easiest part of the process, said Jill Horwitz, a law professor and
founding faculty director of the Lowell-Milken Center for Philanthropy and Nonprofits at the
University of California, Los Angeles. The more complicated part is what would happen to OpenAI's
assets. When such a conversion takes place, it can't simply shift assets from a non-profit to a
for-profit. The non-profit is legally required to end up with assets, including any cash and securities,
at least as valuable as those it turns over, to the for-profit. In effect, OpenAI's operations would
likely be sold to the for-profit company or its investors with the charity retaining the proceeds.
Assets, quote, previously donated to the public benefit cannot be repurposed to private benefit
without compensating the public for the loss, said Alexander Reed, a partner at the law firm
Baker Hostetler. It couldn't be determined how much the remaining non-profit would receive in such a
transaction, given that OpenAI is expected to be valued at around $150 billion after the current
fundraising round. The amount could be immense. That determination is particularly complicated
because the non-profit might own some of OpenAI's patents on AI technology, which would need to be
valued in the conversion. Because most of OpenAI's operations are in California, that state's attorney
general would have jurisdiction to ensure its charitable assets were protected, according to legal experts.
OpenAI hasn't said what the continuing non-profit would do once a profit-seeking company takes over
all of its operations. The current non-profit has supported research on universal basic income
programs and made charitable grants focused on technology and social equality. According to its
website, it could continue to fund such work in the future, using its stake in the for-profit OpenAI
as a source of income. One important issue OpenAI will have to resolve in the conversion is what
rights the non-profit will have to AI technology that the new company develops, end quote.
Men, when we leave the house, it's phone, wallet, keys, how's my hair look right? But if you're
experiencing hair loss, you may not be so confident when you step outside your door. So it's time to get
that confidence back and restore your hair with HIMSS. HIMSS provides access to a range of hair loss
treatments that work, all from the comfort of your couch. HIMSS makes treating hair loss simple with
doctor-trusted treatment options and clinically proven ingredients like finasteride and minoxidil
that can regrow hair in as little as three to six months. They offer personalized chewable oral spray
and serum treatment options so you can find what works best for you. The process is simple and 100%
online. Just answer a few questions and a medical provider will determine if treatment is right for you.
If prescribed, your treatment is sent directly to your door. Start your free online visit today at
HIMSS.com slash ride. That's HIMSS.com slash ride for your personalized hair loss treatment options.
HIMSS.com slash ride. Results vary based on studies of topical and oral minoxidil. Prescription
products require an online consultation with a healthcare provider who will determine if a
prescription is appropriate. Restrictions apply. See website for full details and important safety information.
I'm someone who's rounding my 40s and I'm getting the aches and pains that just won't go away all of a sudden.
Sometimes I just sleep wrong and something will hurt for weeks. So that's why I've been trying
Urolithin A. Urolithin A is a powerful postbiotic that is nearly impossible to get from your diet alone.
And MitoPure from Timeline is the first product to offer a precise dose of Urolithin A to upgrade your
mitochondrial function. Also increase cellular energy and improve muscle strength and endurance.
MitoPure is clinically shown to give our cellular energy generators new power by triggering the body's
natural process for removing and rebuilding damaged mitochondria called mitophagy. By taking two soft gels a day
for two months, you can see significant improvements in your cellular energy, your muscle strength, and your
endurance. After four months of taking MitoPure, you'll feel yourself getting stronger, recovering faster
after a workout, and experiencing less inflammation. All part of your healthier aging routine.
Timeline has MitoPure in two product designs to fit your needs. Their berry powder is great to mix
in with your breakfast yogurt or daily smoothie. And their soft gels are for those days when you're
on the run and want a convenient grab-and-go option. Right now, Timeline is offering 10% off your first
order of MitoPure. Go to timeline.com slash ride. That's t-i-m-e-l-i-n-e dot com slash ride.
If you've searched for some music videos from some high-profile artists recently,
you might have come away disappointed. Why? Well, quoting Variety, songs by Adele, Bob Dylan,
Green Day, REM, Burn a Boy, Rush, and many others are currently unplayable on YouTube in the U.S. due
to a legal dispute between the platform and the performing rights organization, CSAC. Attempts to
play many but not all songs by those artists on Saturday met with the following message.
This video contains content from CSAC. It is not available in your country. A similar dispute
between Universal Music Group and TikTok raged on for several months earlier this year before being
resolved. In a statement to Variety, a YouTube rep said, we have held good faith negotiations with
CSAC to renew our existing deal. Unfortunately, despite our best efforts, we were unable to reach an
equitable agreement before its expiration. We take copyright very seriously, and as a result,
content represented by CSAC is no longer available on YouTube in the U.S. We are in active conversations
with CSAC and are hoping to reach a new deal as soon as possible. Reps for CSAC did not immediately
respond to requests for comment. A source close to the situation tells Variety that the previous deal
actually does not expire until next week and suggests that YouTube's move is a negotiating tactic.
CSAC is far smaller than ASCAP and BMI, with approximately 30,000 members and 1.5 million
compositions, while ASCAP has nearly 800,000 members. But as the caliber of artists affected
by the block shows, it represents a comparatively large percentage of the marketplace."
End quote.
Finally today, I think we've spoken about this before, but maybe not.
Back in September of 2022, the X100 series of point-and-shoot digital cameras went viral on TikTok.
This has led to huge profits for Fujifilm. Imagine that. Huge profits in camera hardware that
isn't a smartphone, quoting Bloomberg.
In September 2022, the photographer and TikTok influencer Kylie Katich posted a video showing off
her Fujifilm X100V.
I just found a camera that will change your life, she told hundreds of thousands of followers at the
time as photos of her infant flashed by. With the warm yellowish glow, the images look like they
could have been pulled out of a photo album from a generation ago. The camera itself, with its jacket
pocket-sized aluminum body, had distinctly vintage features and came programmed with simulations that
mimic the look of photographic film without any editing. It looks like a film camera. It has settings
like a film camera, Katich said in the video, holding up the $1,400 point-and-shoot. It's digital.
Within a day, her post had racked up dozens of comments. Consider me influenced. I am deaf-getting.
One person replied, this is the coolest thing ever, said another.
The endorsement and others like it reverberated through TikTok's sub-communities.
Auto enthusiasts brought their X100Vs to sports car meetups. Musicians took theirs around the world to
document the touring lifestyle. Tech geeks, travel junkies, and fashion influencers all wanted an X100V,
and once they got one, they let their own followers know. The effect on the company's inventory,
already strained by a global chip shortage, was drastic. By November 2022, Fujifilm stopped accepting
online orders for the camera, citing its inability to keep up with demand. Buyers turned to resale
platforms such as eBay, where X100Vs were selling for twice their retail value. Two years later,
TikTok's obsession hasn't slowed, and the manufacturer is still reaping the benefits.
Fujifilm's photo imaging segment brought in $3.3 billion for the fiscal year that ended in March,
a 14.5% year-over-year increase, and was the company's most profitable division for the first
time since at least 2006, when Bloomberg started tracking earnings by segment. Those sales were
driven in part by the X100V's successor. Sporting an upgraded sensor and other new features,
the X100V1, or VI, sold out almost immediately upon its release in February. Both generations
remain unavailable on Fujifilm's website. The company is embracing the camera's coveted status,
and a May earnings call, Chief Executive Officer Tiechi Gotu said the X100Vi's inventory situation was
normal and compared the product's resale value to that of a prestigious competitor. Leica, a well-known
German manufacturer, still maintains a very high value for both their old cameras and the cameras
they sell now, and this is our goal, Gotu said in the call. Fujifilm, which declined requests for
interviews, said in a statement that it's accelerating production to meet demand. Our goal is that every
customer who ordered an X100Vi gets it, the company said, end quote.
Nothing for you today. Talk to you tomorrow.