What a summer of sport!
And now, it's time for the ultimate race day.
Kipco British Champions Day at Ascot Race Force.
See the sport's top stars in action as champions are crowned at the thrilling flat season finale.
Bring your friends and enjoy the ultimate after-party with a DJ set from Hot Chip.
Kipco British Champions Day on Saturday the 19th of October.
Tickets are selling fast.
Book yours from just £32 at BritishChampionsDay.com.
The landmark production of Sam Mendes' The Lehman Trilogy is now playing in London.
The sweeping story of a family and a company that changed the world.
The Wall Street Journal declares it a masterpiece.
A genuinely epic production raves the New York Times.
Behold it with wonder.
Astonishing hails The Guardian.
The Telegraph declares The Lehman Trilogy a masterwork and a must-see.
Now playing at the Gillian Lynn Theatre until January 5th.
Tickets available at thelehmantrilogy.com.
Tickets available at the Gillian Lynn Theatre.
Tickets available at Gillian Lynn Theatre.
!
Hello and welcome to the Tennis Podcast on Monday the 30th of September.
Introduced beautifully there by Marnie.
Marnie says, as a bit of backstory here,
it was very exciting to finally meet you at the US Open this year.
I remember meeting Marnie.
She says, after several years and two continents of looking for you,
we finally ticked that box.
She says her husband, Edwin,
and she started listening to the podcast after reading the New York Times article about the pod.
She says she's proud to be a friend for the last few years.
First picked up a racket ten years ago at the age of 48,
and she absolutely loves it.
She says she'd play every day if she could.
She says, thanks for helping me grow my appreciation of the sport, its history,
and the people in and around the sport through the relived pods.
I cleaned up the intro this year, she says, so there's no confusion.
Even though I live in Houston, I will always be from New Orleans.
And that jogs my memory, Marnie, of the debate we had surrounding your intro last year.
So appreciate that and appreciate your lovely, lilting Southern accent
and your brilliant introduction to the show there.
And of course, if you, dear listener, would like to introduce a show,
then you can do so by becoming a friend of the tennis podcast at intro level,
and you can get access to all of those tennis relived pods
and all of the other bonus content that we produce throughout the year as well.
And that, as always, is in our show notes.
David is here. Hello, David.
Hello. Hello. Yes.
And I'm a bit happier than I was a week ago when I was immediately complaining about the weather.
It hasn't picked up. I've just found my hot water bottles and I'm cuddling them as we speak.
Yes, which makes them sound sort of furry and cosy.
I can tell you folks, they're not. They look sort of, they're quite medical looking in appearance, I would say.
But as long as they're serving a purpose for you, David.
I'm quite new to hot water bottles, so I didn't know they came in different sort of textures.
Just after the sheer heat of it all.
Well, they usually have a little jacket on, don't they? You've got just the innards.
Yes.
But anyway, so long as you're warm, we're all happy.
Matt, how are you? Warm, I hope.
I am warm. I'm wearing my tennis podcast hoodie,
which is normally what you're rocking on one of these podcasts, Catherine.
I thought we were going to be dressed the same on Zoom, but no.
This is a rare week where you're not wearing this exclusive tennis podcast hoodie.
Sorry, that sounded like a bit of a dig to suggest that you only ever wear one item of clothing,
but it wasn't meant to be.
Well, I am wearing Wimbledon merch, so...
That's the other thing you'll wear.
Yeah, it's probably a fair dig.
Certainly a fair genre of dig, anyway.
Folks, it is a complicated week in terms of tennis.
The tournaments that we're watching at the moment, none of them have finished.
One of them is finishing on Wednesday.
Some of them are going for another week.
It's all very confusing.
And we, of course, will be covering off the results from the events that hadn't finished last week
at the time of recording.
We'll cover off what we've seen of Beijing on the men's and women's sides and of Tokyo so far.
And we will be back with a bonus pod this week on Thursday because lots of tennis is happening at weird times.
So we're going to make sure we cover that for you.
So we'll be getting into all of that today and on Thursday.
But I think we have to start with the news that dropped on Saturday morning out of nowhere.
For me, I certainly didn't hear of anybody that knew this was coming.
The news that the World Anti-Doping Agency are appealing the decision to clear Yannick Sinner of blame
after he twice tested positive for a banned substance.
WADA say that last month's ruling by an independent tribunal to fine the Italian World No. 1 had no fault or negligence was, quote,
not correct under the applicable rules.
It is appealed to the court of arbitration for sport and said Sinner should be banned for between one and two years,
although they aren't seeking any retroactive action and they aren't seeking to discredit any of the results that have happened since those positive tests,
i.e. there is no question here whatever the outcome of this appeal of the US Open victory being taken off the books, as it were.
Yannick Sinner released the following statement in response to the news.
He said he's disappointed here that WADA have chosen to appeal the results of the ITIA hearing
after the independent judges had exonerated me and deemed me to be innocent.
Over the past few months and throughout this process, there have been three separate hearings in each case confirming my innocence.
Several months of interviews and investigations culminated in three senior judges scrutinising every detail through a formal hearing.
They issued an in-depth judgment explaining why they determined me not at fault with clear evidence provided and my cooperation throughout.
On the back of such a robust process, both the ITIA and the Italian Anti-Doping Authority accepted it and waived their rights to appeal.
I understand these things need to be thoroughly investigated to maintain the integrity of the sport we all love.
However, it is difficult to see what will be gained by asking a different set of three judges to look at the same facts and documentation all over again.
That being said, I have nothing to hide. And as I have done throughout the summer, I will cooperate fully with the appeal process
and provide whatever may be needed to prove my innocence once again.
As the case is now pending before Cass, I won't comment further.
Now, he states there that the process that's already taken place, the International Tennis Integrity Unit hearing deemed him to be innocent.
Now, according to one interpretation, which is obviously Yannick Sinner's interpretation, that is true.
Innocent, he was cleared of any intentional wrongdoing.
Now, from what I can gather, David, of reading what's come out from WADA, what is at issue here is the extent to which Yannick Sinner is responsible for the actions of his team.
Is that your interpretation as well?
It is, because, look, he had it in his system.
So it's not as though he was just completely found innocent.
Yes, he was found innocent of wrongdoing, of he wasn't found guilty of negligence, as we hear there.
But I can understand why another body looking at the same facts might take the view that, well, you are responsible for the people you hire and they are responsible for having put this in your system.
So, therefore, you are responsible for its existence in your system as well.
I don't think it's a cut and dried case.
And therefore, I'm not actually that surprised that two groups are coming up with different views of this.
And where I would, I mean, on one level, I do feel for him.
It's obviously stressful.
It's obviously wearing.
We heard from him during the US Open.
We found him to be very compelling and kind of convincing in the way that he explained everything.
And then he came and he won the US Open.
But two things that strike me.
One, the idea, as he says, it's difficult to see what will be gained by asking a different set of judges to look at the same facts and documentation all over again.
Well, in that case, you're just completely refuting the idea of appeals.
You're effectively saying, what's the point of appeals given I've already been found innocent of negligence?
So if the shoes on the other foot, therefore, if you got if you got done, are you saying you wouldn't want an appeal because there some judges have already found you innocent or already found you guilty rather?
You know, that's that's that's that's one thing.
And I don't know.
I think that the thing with this is now, if if he does end up having this upheld and doesn't and gets banned, obviously, if you were to be banned, that's that's significant impact to his career.
But I do think historically you would then have to look at his US Open with an asterisk, even if they're not taking it away from him and they're not seeking to disqualify it.
Everybody would know that the end result.
If it had been found in the first instance, would would have meant you wouldn't have competed in that US Open.
So so this is this is massively significant.
Now, he may well now get this this appeal heard and refuted as well.
So he may end up coming out in exactly the same position.
And then that would be that.
But it might not.
And there's going to be a period now he is eligible to play.
But and I understand why he doesn't want to talk about it anymore while this is ongoing.
But it does mean that every time he plays, that just has to be in the back of your mind somewhere, because this is pending.
And and who knows how long this is going to take?
You know, I spent quite a long time with with the communications officer for the International Tennis Integrity Agency during the US Open.
And and I just heard just how difficult these these cases are to to to to undergo and put together and how long it takes.
And I and I was saying, well, why don't you and Cass spend time together and work it out and and get a get more of a common idea?
And and he said they don't want to speak.
We don't have any contact with them at all.
They won't they won't talk to us.
So, yeah, who knows how long this is going to take?
And look, in terms of it it weighing on him, we just watched him beat Yuri Lahechka 6276 to reach the semifinals in Beijing, just as we now know was the case throughout the summer and was winning Cincinnati.
And his on court results so far seem remarkably untouched by by this off court drama is an interesting point you make about sort of the appeals process and sort of what's the point in in different eyes looking at the same case in in the court of law to appeal.
You do have to have fresh evidence.
You can't just ask for someone else to have a different different look at a case and see if they view it differently.
You have to present something something new.
But I believe that's not the case in this situation.
What they're actually not asking the evidence to be reexamined in terms of what happened is my understanding.
I think that's not the case in this situation.
Maybe we are due an examination of this bigger picture issue.
And it does sound like that is going to be at the heart of this
Court of Arbitration for Sport hearing.
Absolutely.
And I suppose I was probably quite quick to just very much kind of agree
with what Yannick Sinner said during that US Open, which was,
we know the source.
It was members of my team.
And I've got rid of those team members.
And, you know, I sort of took Sinner's word on that.
But it is an important question, I suppose.
If you accept, as the ITIA and WADA both do,
that Sinner himself didn't intend to enhance his performance,
then there's still a couple of possible plausible scenarios
which need examining.
There's a situation where his fitness trainer and physio at the time,
and Bartow Ferrara and Iacomo Naldi didn't intend to enhance Sinner's performance.
But Naldi unknowingly massaged Sinner with Klosterball from the spray that Ferrara had bought.
And so it was all a complete accident.
But that's why Sinner tested positive.
And that's what the team have said happened.
But there's also scenario B where it was intentional on the part of Sinner's team to enhance his performance behind Sinner's back,
but using Klosterball to help him gain an edge.
Now, we don't know the answer to that.
It's not what's on trial.
But the question of whether Sinner, as the employer of those team members,
is responsible for their actions is the crux of this.
And I think it's reasonable that WADA, a different body, has come to a different conclusion
because you don't want a sport where scenario B is happening all the time.
And to prevent that, one way might be to say that a player is responsible
and should face consequences for their team's actions, no matter whether they knew about it or not,
and no matter whether those actions from the team were intentional or not.
Yeah, like just optically, this news dropping was pretty shocking
because it felt like Beijing was kind of the moment for Yannick Sinner to move on from this
because he's literally sitting there with his new team members,
Marco Panicci and Ulysses Badio, who are very familiar from a coaching box perspective
because they've been in Novak Djokovic's box for a long, long time.
And he's hired the people that Novak Djokovic had with him to replace Ferrara and Naldi.
And he's sort of literally on court with them in this sort of moving on from the case.
And yet this news drops and we know how much, OK, it hasn't affected his results, as we've seen.
He's currently on a 14 match winning streak.
He was winning things before the world knew about this case.
He was winning things after the world knew about this case.
But we know that it's taken a toll on him personally.
You know, he's spoken about that and how he has, you know, sort of shrunk his world.
And I feel like eventually that might sort of catch up with him.
And it's just sort of it's a lot for him to to be processing and have going on right now.
And yeah, like for sure, it's a big moment, because if if the world number one ends up getting banned for a long time,
then we've obviously got this, you know, that changes the complexion of men's tennis going forward.
And as David said, it would it would change how we view this year as well, because if Wilder's verdict had been come to in the first place,
then he wouldn't have been playing the US Open that he ended up winning.
So it's a massive moment for the sport.
And I think you're absolutely right that it does raise that huge question of how responsible are our players for the actions of their team members.
You know, we we credit coaches, don't we, when when when players do good things on court and therefore should we be holding the players responsible when their coaches maybe do something that's that's wrong,
like like they've done in this case or not his coaches, but his, you know, his team.
So it's it's incredibly complicated that that question.
And I'm not I suppose the issue I have is like there isn't a clear cut answer.
So if he does end up getting banned, it will kind of feel a little bit unfair.
And if he doesn't end up getting banned, you also think, well, maybe that's kind of wrong as well.
Like just such a such a difficult place to come down on one side, I think, which makes it so hard.
Yeah, I agree. I think if if Wada win this appeal, I will have a lot of sympathy for Yannick Sinner a lot.
But equally, I think it's very important for the integrity of the sport going forward that it is not possible.
And I'm absolutely not suggesting this is what's happened with Yannick Sinner.
I'm just saying that this principle of the responsibility you have for your team.
I think I think this could set quite a precedent because I as I was saying, I think it's very important for the integrity of the sport, any sport,
that it is not possible just to have a don't ask, don't tell policy with the people you employ.
Because I do think that opens a gateway to to a defense, cheating defense, basically to, you know, I'm employing you.
Just make me the best tennis player I can be. I don't need I don't need to know the details.
So I think it's very, very important that that is not possible and admissible within the rules.
But for Yannick Sinner to potentially be the landmark case to set that example and make that statement is is quite a thing.
And David, well, you've touched upon it in terms of, you know, looking how the US Open victory would be viewed if this wider appeal is successful.
But this is just a disaster for tennis, isn't it? It just looks so bad for tennis.
If the appeal is successful, it'll look bad for the tennis integrity agency. It'll look bad for tennis.
It'll make records a nightmare. You know, whenever you see a graphic of numbers of Grand Slams won, you'll always do a bit of mental gymnastics for the US Open asterisk.
Will there be a world number one asterisk? It's just a nightmare for the sport.
Yeah, nobody's winning here at all. I do share your view about somehow the need to get to a bit more of a conclusive view over what is and isn't negligence and just have that as the rule so that everybody understands where they where they are.
But but but but you're right. I mean, having spent this time with with the rep, Adrian Bassett from the International Tennis Integrity Agency, I mean, he was saying, you know, we'll we'd be happy to have you in and talk to you about you could grill us speak to us about any elements of this that you want.
You know, we obviously we can't talk about specific cases, but how we work and all this sort of stuff.
You can you can you can feel their frustration at not being able to to to to be to have the trust of the sport and the fans and the players and everybody in the way that they'd love the process to have the trust.
And I'm afraid there isn't there isn't a way you can trust feel completely confident given the number of cases that are going to Cass and just being completely overruled with massive discrepancies.
See the Salona Halep case. So, yeah, well, all we can do is wait, wait and find out what comes out of this.
But it's it's a big blow. No question.
She's she's she's due to start playing again next week.
I think Halep, isn't she? Did I did I see that?
No, that's right.
I mean, interesting off the court on the court, but obviously off the court.
That means, you know, she's going to be doing some press, isn't she?
Yeah.
Well, we might get to hear more of her views on on a thing or two.
OK, well, look, we will follow that very closely and keep you posted on it.
There is no timeline at the moment for that hearing, as is well documented.
It's very much a how long is a piece of string thing.
So for the moment, it hangs over the sport and it hangs over Yannick Sinner.
Should we stay in the vaguely legal domain?
Why not?
For our next news item.
Wimbledon's plans to expand.
This is from various reporting in the UK press, including on the BBC and The Guardian.
And from me personally, I attended some of this hearing virtually before deciding it was simply too boring and tapping out to go for a wet dog walk.
But I did do some hashtag journalism here.
Wimbledon's expansion plans have been given the green light after the deputy mayor of London, Jules Pipe, ruled at the end of a three hour public hearing at City Hall that the, quote,
very significant benefits of the scheme outweighed any potential harm to the environment.
And there were some protesters present.
There were some boos from the gallery when this verdict came down, a verdict that had felt a bit of a foregone conclusion on the day.
Certainly there had been some briefing going on that this was going to be the likely outcome.
But there were protests.
And I know, you know, from personal experience, there is a strong depth of feeling from those that are opposed, including the local MP, Fleur Anderson, who remains opposed to the plan and spoke on Friday against it.
The plans include growing from 41 to 115 hectares on the site of the old Wimbledon Park golf course.
Do you think there's any other countries in the world that use hectares as a unit of measurement?
Does anybody outside of the UK know what we're talking about?
Do I even know what we're talking about?
I wrote it in the agenda and have absolutely no concept of what it means.
It's getting bigger.
That's what I can tell you.
You are welcome.
Almost trebling, almost trebling in size.
According to my maths.
They're building 39 new courts, including one 8000 seater permanent structure that'll have a roof.
They'll be bringing qualifying on site and allowing 10,000 people a day to attend.
That's up from the 2000 people a day that are able to attend qualifying currently at Roehampton.
It'll increase the grounds capacity to 50,000 per day during the main championships.
And they'll be upgrading the facilities for all the players.
The AELTC's chief executive, Sally Bolton, is thrilled, obviously.
It's fantastic news, she says.
We've got some legal agreements to work through.
Then we can look forward to delivering one of the greatest transformations since the London Games,
which I think we're all very excited about delivering.
There is still the possibility of a judicial review, an appeal, essentially.
An attempt could be made to challenge the lawfulness of the way the decision was made on the grounds of illegality, procedural unfairness or irrationality.
But the bar remains high as any very small number of these cases succeed each year.
I think it's fewer than 10% in terms of judicial reviews that are accepted.
So I guess no one will relax, given the bumpy road that this has been until the threat of judicial review is gone.
But it looks almost certainly like this is happening.
And look, as I said, there is strong feeling against locally.
But we are a tennis podcast.
And in terms of tennis and Wimbledon, this is good news, David.
Yeah.
I mean, I do try to keep that in mind.
But on a very selfish level, as somebody who cares about the sport, this is brilliant news.
I'm not personally affected by it in the area.
I understand that.
Obviously, there is a green belt question mark that some would have.
And I understand that.
Although the plans that I've seen and people that I've spoken to, it does feel like there's a real understanding of the importance of creating parkland within this new development.
And I mean, I just cannot believe that Wimbledon won't make this beautiful and special and really something and ultimately way, way better than it was before.
And from a sporting perspective, I think Debbie Jevons, the chair, is absolutely right.
And it's become more apparent than ever this year that Wimbledon was falling behind in terms of that third week in particular.
You know, it's been creeping for a while, ever since the Australian Open first started staging practice matches in the lead up to the Australian Open.
And then the US Open starting to try to launch its fan week.
But it was when the French Open opened up qualifying to everybody and started sticking the whole thing in court, Susan Longland for 12,000 people to come out and watch first round qualifying.
That I just knew that, OK, Grand Slam's are three weeks now.
And they're constantly trying to one up each other.
And even assuming all of this goes ahead as planned and is available for Wimbledon between 2030 and 2033, imagine how much progress these other Grand Slams are going to make in the next six to nine years on developing their week before.
Now, I think because Wimbledon will be building at the same time, I can only imagine how special it will be the day that Wimbledon finally opens the doors for that extra week.
And I suspect that all of those six to nine years, you will then on that moment think, ah, OK, we see where all this has been building towards.
It's to this moment and it's worth it.
But they're going to have to put up with another six to nine years of frustration whilst all the other Grand Slam's are making strides.
I think as long as this goes through, they will be able to think and we will all be able to think, yeah, but at least they're able to do it now and it'll be worth it in the end.
But, yeah, I think the stakes are really quite high for Wimbledon here.
Huge, in fact.
And in terms of judicial review, we will, of course, keep you posted.
That's it for the legal segment of the podcast, the procedural segment.
A couple of other bits of news before we talk about results from the week that has just been.
Rafael Nadal has been picked for Spain's Davis Cup finals squad.
Could we get the Alca, no, oh, no.
Nadal Caraz.
Could we get the Nadal Caraz, Nadal retirement that we deserve, Matt, in Malaga?
Well, as I said before, Spain literally have the doubles world number one at the moment, who is Marcel Granollas.
And yet, I think, yes, I think we probably will get Nadal and Alca's doubles if it comes to that.
I mean, if you're David Ferrer, how could you not pick that team if it's available to you?
Like, I just think that would be incredibly hard to resist.
Alca has certainly spoke about this in Beijing and Alca has is up for it.
He said he missed Nadal at Leiva Cup and he hopes to play with him in Malaga.
I think that probably probably is the only way we would be seeing Nadal like actually play barring injury.
I just think, you know, indoor hard court has never been Nadal's best surface anyway.
And obviously, Alca has is an absolute lock to play singles.
And Roberto Bautista Agu in the last few weeks has started winning some, you know, some quite impressive matches again.
And he's probably going to be their number two singles player, I would have thought.
So, you know, David Ferrer, when he announced this team, he very much saved Nadal till last and put him in as the as the kind of fifth pick.
And I think he's there in that role.
He's he's going to bring the vibes.
He's going to bring the energy and if he's available and ready to play doubles, he's going to be fired up and most likely taken to court in the doubles.
I suppose there's potentially a chance that we see Nadal and Granoyes.
Like because Alcares has not shown himself to be a particularly brilliant doubles player.
But as I said, how can you resist Nadal and Alcares?
I don't think Ferrer is the guy that's going to go, Carlos, sorry, no, you're on the bench for this one.
Marcel, you're on.
I just I just don't think David Ferrer is is going to do that.
Matt, you're.
Great options though, aren't they?
Yes.
You know, you've suddenly actually got yourself some options there.
Like if Nadal and Alcares got a little tweak or something like that.
Or if he's played like a three and a half hour singles match and, you know, they need to protect him a little bit.
Like you're being very dismissive, Matt, of the Saudi Kings because Nadal is the, I think, second seed at the Saudi Kings.
He's scheduled to play singles.
Is that right?
Wow.
In just a few weeks time.
Yeah.
Nadal and Djokovic are the top seeds suspiciously and they get a bye through to the semifinals.
This is the exhibition tournament featuring.
Like a bus pass.
Featuring six, six top male tennis players, although Holger Rune should have very pleased to be their energy throughout the entire experience.
I've just watched him lose to a sort of one legged artifice.
Yeah.
And I mentioned it because, well, the draw came out this week, but also their eye-wateringly expensive looking promo feature film dropped this week and is making some waves on the internet.
And Nadal is playing.
Singles.
Second seed.
Yes.
That's what being Saudi Arabia's tennis ambassador gets you, I suppose.
The second seed in that.
I think they've done seeding on the basis of age and injury from what I can gather.
Number of grand slam titles.
Who is physically able to play three matches?
No, not you two?
Okay.
Right.
Yeah.
I mean, some people are going nuts for this promo video.
And look, it's, as I said, it's dripping in money.
But all I saw when I watched it was sort of sadness that, oh, well, people do have, like, just all this money being spent on tennis that's being spent on that tennis by those people.
Like, oh, this is what's possible.
Can't we have some cleaner, cleaner, less problematic money?
I don't know.
Just depressing, isn't it?
But anyway, I digress.
We will get to see, hopefully, some wholesome Nadal Karaz in November in Malaga.
Last bit of news before we move on to results and on-court stuff.
Bit of a tough one here.
A social media post from Caroline Garcia announcing that she's shutting down her season.
She says, I'm tired of living in a world where my worth is measured by last week's results, my ranking, or my unforced errors.
Mentally, I need a reset.
I need to step away from the constant grind of tennis.
I'm exhausted from the anxiety, the panic attacks, the tears before matches.
I'm tired of missing out on family moments and never having a place to truly call home.
Physically, I've been pushing my shoulder to its limit, trying to recover while competing, and it's just not working.
I need more time off to heal properly.
In my mind, I've been stuck on what I haven't achieved.
I never made it to number one, never won a single slam, never reached an Olympic podium.
I've been inconsistent, unable to stay in the top ten for a full year.
I'm choosing to step away now.
I'm taking a few weeks off to recharge.
Then I'll start preparing for 2025 early, getting ready physically, mentally, and tactically.
It's a bit of a kind of portrait of a modern tennis player, that, isn't it?
Because so many lines in there are familiar.
Thankfully, some of them are familiar from players who have kind of been through that emotional experience of feeling like their worth is measured by their results.
And having come out on the other side, or at least kind of mentally worked through those feelings in therapy or whatever.
But it was alarming how familiar those words felt to me.
And I don't know what the answer is, because it is just an unbelievably demanding sport.
But it's difficult to know whether this is a worsening situation or whether it is players, people generally now have better language for these things and feel more able to express these things publicly, which is a very, very good thing that we're hearing about this more.
And we should make, therefore, more accommodation for it.
But it is alarming, David.
Yeah, as you were reading those quotes out, I was thinking they feel like the definitive version of what it is like to be a tennis player behind the scenes.
If you actually look in the mirror and are honest with yourself about how you're feeling.
On the negative side, listen, there are loads of positive sides to this as well, to being a tennis player.
But so often, even now, so often you get the Instagram version of what it is like to be a tennis player.
And I think, really, over the years, that's what we've got more often than not with Caroline Garcia.
She has her own hashtag, Fly With Caro.
And she's often sort of following up a loss with a tweet which says, on to the next one, and all the rest of it, which, of course, you have to feel as well.
But I've often got the feeling that, really, are you able to just put it behind you as quickly as that?
And, I mean, in more recent times, I have seen other posts from her, and she's got her own podcast in which she's obviously, she's often examining mental health with other tennis players.
But right here, I feel like you've got from her what has probably, well, what has been going on in her mind and in the background all along.
And which I think is probably going on for a lot of players.
And if you ask, well, what's the kind of plus side, what's the end game to something like this, what's the answer, maybe it's for other players to have to read what she's got to say as somebody who's been on the tour for 10 years.
And for them to acknowledge the dangers and the risks and the sort of the importance of taking breaks and not just giving in to the tour treadmill.
You know, we always say there's too much tennis and we sometimes have a go for players for them playing exhibitions.
It's still not the same, is it?
You could, if you want, you can take a break.
And yes, you may take a rankings hit.
And I do think maybe the sport needs to look at ways of not clobbering people rankings wise or financially if they don't turn up at a tournament so that they can have breaks more easily.
But I do think empowering players, empowering teams and families to be able to look at the words of Caroline Garcia and think, you know what, I think you're at risk of what she's describing there or I'm at risk of it and I need to stop for a bit.
And I think that that should hopefully be helped by what she's just done.
Yeah. And just on the subject of players playing exhibitions and thus kind of weakening their argument about the amount of tennis and the length of the season and the demands of that on modern players.
A few male players have talked about that this week.
It does feel like that's coming to the fore a bit as a talking point.
Taylor Fritz made the point on Twitter that exhibitions just are not comparable to tour events in terms of the mental and physical fatigue.
He says, an exo, you show up, have some fun and entertain for a match or two.
You don't have to all out push your body and there is absolutely zero mental fatigue or stress.
In a lot of ways, an exo is a lot like a rest week, he says, and shouldn't be compared with a tour event.
I don't expect non-players to fully comprehend what I mean by this because it's tough to judge the mental and physical fatigue that playing at tour weeks entails if you're not a part of it.
But I would fully expect players to understand what I mean by this.
And I do think that's a valid point.
I still don't think it's the same as, you know, a proper break from the sport or even a proper block of time to make technical adjustments to your game.
I mean, that's simply not really possible without taking a break from the sport at the moment.
But I do think that's a valid point Taylor Fritz makes that we should take into consideration.
Denis Shapovalov made a slightly different defence of exhibitions.
He said, in my opinion, if players would make decent money during the season, they wouldn't feel the need to play exos in off weeks.
Instead, players, aside from maybe the top 20, only make decent money four times a year.
Slams.
So it's a no-brainer for players to play exos for good cash.
And then in reply to somebody else, he said, who was pointing out, you know, how much money tennis players make.
He said, yeah, but take up taxes, percentages, salaries and expenses we play.
Tennis isn't like other sports where you keep the money you make.
There are a lot of costs as a tennis player.
Not saying we don't make money, just that we make much more money than much more money playing exos.
Not saying there isn't a grain of validity in that, but just a couple of counterpoints to Denis Shapovalov there.
Number one, like it is the top 20 players in the world that generally are invited to play exhibitions.
Like Liam Brody ain't getting invited to play many exhibitions.
It is the top players that the Saudi kings want to come and play.
Sorry, the kings are the players themselves, aren't we?
It is the Saudi kings, Nadal and Djokovic et al, that are paid the big bucks for exhibitions.
And number two, last time I checked, which was this week, so it's possible the internet isn't up to date,
but Denis Shapovalov lives in Bahamas, which is a tax haven.
And even if he didn't live in a tax haven, like, yeah, we all pay taxes, mate.
That's a thing for everyone.
I think that's a really fun new pod segment.
Catherine community notes.
Well, any tennis player's tweets, but Denis Shapovalov's in particular.
Did you see Sitsapass's tweet this week about the schedule, which was just lifted from AI,
just fully, fully just written by AI, chatty Cathy or something?
I don't know what it is, but like, because I will read a 1,000 word article or 500 word article, no problem.
But if I see a tweet that's longer than 280 characters, I just don't read it.
It's just too, it's just not the place.
He wrote an absolute essay on there.
And I just couldn't get through any of it.
He didn't.
And, no.
No, he lifted it from AI.
He could have said to AI, make it a length that Matt Roberts feels comfortable with.
AI would have been capable of that.
Am I the only one, though?
Do you not feel that when you see a really long tweet?
You just immediately just go, oh, close it.
It's just, yeah.
Not what I came here for.
The reason you have to click for more, Matt, is because they're not designed to be read like that.
Yeah, agreed.
Right, that's your news for this week.
We'll be back in part two with some tennis to talk about.
What a summer of sports.
And now it's time for the ultimate race day.
Kipco British Champions Day, a task at Race Sports.
See the sport's top styles in action as champions are crowned at the thrilling flat season finale.
Bring your friends and enjoy the ultimate after party with a DJ set from Hot Chip.
Kipco British Champions Day on Saturday the 19th of October.
Tickets are selling fast.
Book yours for just £32 at BritishChampionsDay.com.
It's a little cold, a little grey.
But you and your potential aren't letting anything get in your way.
No, today you're going to boost your skill set and your wages with free courses for jobs or a free skills boot camp.
Designed to fit around life, you could even get help with childcare or travel.
So go on, see which training option can help you make the most of your potential.
It all starts with skills.
Search skills for life.
Hey, I'm Jay Comfrey, host of High Performance.
And I'm excited to tell you about a brand new series we've created in collaboration with Lloyds Bank from Startup to Standout.
Lloyds Bank know there are plenty of British business success stories out there.
And that's why over the last few months, we've been working together to make a brand new mini series entitled From Startup to Standout.
A four episode series that sees me and the team visit a different business supported by Lloyds Bank each week,
meeting their team and understanding how they navigated those tricky early years.
So if you want to hear me visiting a company making material made from seaweed to develop new packaging solutions,
a firm changing the marketing game, a bistro run by husband and wife and a plant powered hair care brand.
Tune in to From Startup to Standout by searching for it in your podcast apps or find us on the High Performance podcast feed or on the High Performance YouTube channel.
Welcome back to the tennis podcast part two, talking about the tennis that we've seen in the last week.
None of the none of this week's tournaments have ended yet, but some of last week's tournaments did finally come to an end.
David, a week ago, we were talking about your dashed hopes of watching Marin Cilic in a final.
Well, I don't know whether you manifested it, but your dreams did come true.
You did get to see Marin Cilic in a final and he won that final, thus becoming at 777 in the world,
the lowest ranked ATP title winner in history.
He beat Zheng Zhijian 7-6, 7-6 to win the title in Hwangzhou.
Dreams do come true.
And it was so lovely.
It was so lovely to see Marin Cilic happy.
I mean, you know, I'm sure he spent lots of his last two years happy privately when he wasn't trying to come back from being a tennis player.
I mean, he's got a good life, I think.
But I haven't seen him for 20 months because he hasn't been on a tennis court and I don't see him socially.
And it's not like the paparazzi are hanging out outside his apartment to get me new pictures of Marin Cilic.
So this is the first time I've seen him in a long time and I really loved it.
And I actually quite enjoy watching Marin Cilic play anyway.
But I really thought he was finished.
I didn't think he'd get through this latest injury.
You know, 20 months is a long time, isn't it?
And to come out and be able to play at this level, I know it's a few weeks in the making.
It's not been instant.
But to beat a player like Zheng Zhijian like that, that's pretty impressive.
And then he came out and he played Nishikori this week.
That was excellent.
But yeah, he just seemed so thrilled to be back and winning a title.
That was quite a good tennis match, Cilic Nishikori.
I tuned in for the lols and I ended up watching it just for genuine tennis enjoyment.
So more fool me.
A Chinese finalist in Hwangzhou and a Chinese champion in Chengdu, Jerry Shang,
becoming the first Chinese player to win an ATP title on home soil.
He beat Lorenzo Mazzetti 7-6, 6-1.
I'd still, Matt, call that a good week for Mazzetti, reaching a hard court final.
But clearly an even better week for the very talented Jerry Shang.
Yeah, he's got a bit of a final problem, Mazzetti, at the moment.
He's reached a lot of finals this year on one level or another and he keeps losing them.
But I agree with you.
I think it is another sign of kind of the strides he's making.
Even though he was the top seed, I think Mazzetti top seed on a hard court,
it wouldn't really have backed him in the past to sort of even get to the final.
But the fact that he did was a sign that he is playing a lot better.
But he was outclassed in this final.
Shang probably should have won the first set before even needing a tie break.
He served for it and then got broken back,
but then did win that tie break and absolutely ran through the second set.
And he only dropped one set in the entire tournament, did Shang.
And like beat lots of different types of player as well.
Beat Nishikori in the first round who sort of,
that has aged a lot better than it did at the time.
I thought, oh, a win over Kane Nishikori.
But as you said, the tennis that Nishikori's been playing
in these past couple of weeks has been fantastic.
He was so good in Tokyo.
And Shang had beat him in Chengdu.
He also beat Bublik, who he's played quite a bit this year.
And yeah, he's, I think, the second youngest in the top 100.
He very nearly beat Kasper Rude at the US Open
before sort of fading physically.
But I think he's coming, Jerry Shang.
Like I think he's quite slight.
And I can imagine that that jump from sort of the juniors to the pros might,
like it's obviously going well.
He's young, he's 19.
Like it's not been a really hard transition for him.
But I can imagine that when he's playing these pros week in, week out,
he might have kind of felt that slightness, I suppose.
But as he continues to develop physically,
I think he's got the game and he's got the smarts.
And I just think he's going to be a bit of a star.
Like he's got charisma.
I think the ATP really like him.
They really use him in a lot of their social media content and videos.
And great for him to have a moment in his home country.
And yeah, he's very much sort of on the radar, I think, for next year to,
what is he now, around about 50 in the world.
I think he's going to be looking to try and get inside the top 20,
I would have thought, next year.
Kei Nishikori went on to Tokyo, as you said.
And there was a moment after he'd beaten Marin Cilic
and backed that up with a win over Jordan Thompson
that I got really into the Kei Nishikori comes back,
wins his home tournament narrative.
But by the time I got into it, it was all but over.
Ended up losing out to Holger Runa in the quarterfinals,
who I've just watched out, watched David,
and I'm sure you have as well, lose out to Artur Fies,
who now finds himself in the final to play fellow Frenchman Ugo Mbair.
7-6, 7-6 for Fies over Runa,
having beaten Ben Shelton yesterday in an extraordinary match.
On the basis of what I just saw at the end of that Runa match, though,
I am backing Mbair in this final
because he looks physically absolutely shot.
But whatever happens in that final,
and we'll cover it on Thursday's show,
this feels like a big week for a man.
Yeah, and listen, he did look pretty shot yesterday
against Ben Shelton at the end and came back.
I think this was cramp by the looks of what I saw at the end of that
really long tiebreak set against Holger Runa.
It has been a long week for Fies.
It's one of those where I think it's a little misleading
that he's in the final and he's beaten Taylor Fritz,
Matteo Berrettini, Ben Shelton, Holger Runa.
It's a fantastic cast list, isn't it,
of players to beat to reach a final.
But you also have to consider the circumstances.
Taylor Fritz in his first match off the Lever Cup,
literally a day or two later,
I think that that probably has played a factor.
Matteo Berrettini actually won the first set against him
and then had to retire due to injury.
Although I did feel like Fies should have won that set.
I've watched all of these matches, obviously.
And Shelton could have beaten him as well,
even though I don't think that that would have been right if he had.
I think Fies was the better player.
He had 19 break points to just three of Shelton's.
So it was really close in the end, tiebreak in the third.
But he was the better.
This is the best I've seen Fies play.
He obviously won the Hamburg tournament.
That was a big deal.
But the first time I've seen him on a hard court
where his game just isn't breaking down,
there isn't any of the rally shots going into the net
or long in quite the same way as there was,
certainly in the first part of the year.
He's not missing return after return
the way he was for the first three months of the year.
There have been adjustments made, technically.
I'm not equipped well enough to know exactly what they are,
but he works with Sébastien Grosjean.
And you can just see that the game isn't breaking down.
He looks solid.
And you add that to the natural athleticism.
I mean, he's got to be one of the most explosive
athletic specimens in tennis.
And he's also just got that chutzpah as well.
You know, he just wants to come and have it with you.
And him and Shelton, you could tell,
just have a real buzz about playing against each other.
So, no, I think this is massive.
But Umber has beaten him comfortably in the past
when they've played.
So, I would imagine Umber is the favourite.
And this is an occasion for me to roll out
one of my very favourite stats,
which is that Ugo Umber has never lost an ATP final.
He's six from six.
And no one has ever won their first seven.
The other two players to have won their first six,
I remember this stat from earlier in the year
when Umber won his sixth final.
The other two players are Martin Klijan and Ernest Golbis.
Like, it's not a list of all-time greats.
But Umber is looking to become the first guy
to win their first seven ATP finals.
And I watched him today beat the best player in the world
in three sets.
And he has an ability, Umber,
to suddenly lift his level
and start hitting so cleanly,
especially down the line.
He makes it seem really easy.
But he can reel off winners
kind of in a seemingly effortless way.
His timing is so impressive on the ball.
But he's got this weird thing going on, Umber.
Maybe it's not that weird.
Maybe it's quite telling about him as a player.
But he's playing his best tennis
at the least important times in the season.
You know, he is...
He's very good in that February-March period,
you know, where he won Marseille and Dubai
earlier this year.
And last year, in this sort of September-October-November period,
he won Mets.
Now he's in the final of Tokyo.
He kind of disappears over the summer,
like the most important time.
Like, he did well at Wimbledon this year.
He got to the fourth round and pushed Alcaraz.
Like, that was a good performance.
But he's got to start playing his best tennis
at the most important tournaments
because his top level is really good.
But, you know, Grand Sam's summer season,
he's sort of nowhere to be seen.
But, you know, it's September-October tennis again
and here he is lighting it up.
And, yeah, like, I think he's probably got the physical edge
over Feast in this final.
But I'm looking forward to it.
They're kind of in many, certainly recently,
finals between two French players.
So that'll be interesting.
Yeah, for sure.
Staying with the men over in Beijing,
they are at the semi-final stage.
The quarter-finals have been played today.
The last one is still on court.
It looks like Buwen Shaokete
is going to beat Andrei Robloff
and set up a semi-final with Yannick Senna.
The other semi, Daniel Medvedev,
who beat Flavio Caboli
to take on Carlos Alcaraz,
who's just cruised through the draw this week
and looks so refreshed, David.
I mean, yeah, I can't remember the last time
I saw Carlos Alcaraz look this fresh and loose.
And I include his two Grand Sam titles this season in that.
Yeah, it's interesting, isn't it?
Trying to work out what is the recipe
for being fresh and loose,
particularly, I mean, the ADB put together
that really great video of jet lag effects
and everybody looking exhausted.
And then at the end,
Carlos Alcaraz looking like he's just
having the best time
and he's got loads of energy.
It was really well put together.
But why did he hit the wall
at certain stages in the last season,
at the end of last season?
I know he was injured as well,
but he looked exhausted at the end of last season.
Obviously, he hit the wall
and was poor at the US Open.
Why has he suddenly got energy again?
Who knows?
You know how these things work
when you feel good and when you don't.
But goodness me,
when he does feel good,
you can tell.
You can just see it coming out of every pore
in his body language.
And when he's like that,
he's unstoppable, I think.
I mean, I just can't.
I can't get enough of watching it.
I mean, between him and Karolina Mukhera,
you know, just players that I would just turn on
to watch them perform.
Simple as.
You know, I don't care who they're playing.
And yeah, long may that continue, really.
I mean, and obviously,
because we want to see Alcaraz
against the other best players in the world
and I want to see him play Yannick Sinner.
And yet I still have this uneasy feeling now
because suddenly this case has reared its head again.
Very small thing on Alcaraz.
I didn't watch his,
I didn't see his match today against Hakshinov,
but the other ones in Beijing,
he hasn't had the strapping on his upper thigh,
which I mean, certainly all through the summer,
he's had that.
As you say, Catherine,
even when he's been winning Grand Sam titles,
he's been playing with that on his leg.
And yeah, like just another sign,
I think that he's freer, looser, fresher, fitter.
And yeah, as you say,
that's bad news for everyone else
because when Alcaraz is in that mood,
I mean, yeah, how do you stop him?
And it's still a first, isn't it?
We've never seen him play well
at this time of the season before.
We're still seeing first from Carlos Alcaraz,
extraordinary.
The reason presumably, Matt,
that you weren't watching Alcaraz against Hakshinov
is because you were watching Amanda Anisimova
continue to make Dariya Kazakina her pigeon.
That's 10 sets played, 10 sets won
by Amanda Anisimova against Dariya Kazakina.
She is through to the round of 16 in the women's
where she'll face Zheng Chin Wen.
So the men are at the semi-final stage.
The women are at the round of 16 stage
with still another week to go in Beijing.
Of course, for the women, it's a 1,000 event.
For the men, it's just a 500.
Quote from Matt,
I'm fed up of seeing Zheng Chin Wen beat my faves.
It's just happened a lot this summer.
What can I say?
Well, yeah, because it's the US Open rematch,
isn't it, from the first round.
Anisimova was cruising against Zheng Chin Wen,
upper set, 6-1.
What could have been had Anisimova managed to close that match?
But I think, you know, we've talked a lot
sort of privately this week about the vibes in Beijing
kind of missing.
You know, there's just,
you've got this enormous stadium there.
Like, it's vast.
And yet, it's pretty empty for most of these matches.
Apart from the Zheng Chin Wen matches,
they are showing up for her and filling it.
And it's an incredible sight to see that much support for her.
And I can imagine that she'd be much better equipped now
at this stage in her career to sort of embrace that support.
I think having won the gold medal,
I think she really has sort of kind of grown in stature on the court.
And I think it is kind of boosting her, that support.
And I think that's going to be a lot for Anisimova
to have to deal with.
I think that matches in a couple of days' time.
But yeah, there's some really good last 16 matches set up in Beijing.
Yeah, she is not the only Chinese woman
still in the draw in Beijing.
In fact, she's not even, for my money,
the headline Chinese woman left in the draw in Beijing.
Zhang Shuai, ladies and gentlemen,
is into the Beijing round of 16
to face Magdalena Frech later on today.
After losing 24 matches in a row,
she scored her first singles victory in 603 days,
beating McCartney Kessler 7-6-6-1.
And then she went on to be Emma Navarro
and Grit Minnan all in straight sets.
I feel like this is a period
that should be studied for kind of sports science PhDs,
like the art of...
or the unknowable mistress that is confidence and momentum
encapsulated in one human being that is Zhang Shuai.
I watched that match through gritted teeth against McCartney Kessler
just because I think I floated the idea during the US Open.
She might never end this run.
She might have to retire and not be able to end it on tour level
because she's going to lose a ranking eventually
and all this sort of thing.
And suddenly she's in this big tournament.
She's got the wild card.
And she managed to get over the line.
And you should have seen her body language when she did it
because suddenly she couldn't stop talking in the on-court interview.
And she took the mic and did her own thing.
It was like an audience with Zhang Shuai.
And it was just wonderful.
And then, yeah, the next thing I know,
I didn't bother watching the next one
because she's already broken the streak
and she's just kind of destroyed Emma Navarro 6462.
Like it's nothing.
So, yeah.
And the thing is, she didn't become a bad player.
She's always been a good player, a great backhand,
you know, good watch.
And now she's suddenly unencumbered by all this stress
and it's happening.
Yeah, it's so, it's just tennis, isn't it?
And she spoke about how everyone in the locker room
was so pleased for her when she got back in there.
They were all greeting her.
And I actually had a look at what Vincent Spadia did
after he broke his 21-match losing streak.
I thought, you know, maybe, you know,
maybe he then went on an incredible run.
But he did not.
He lost his very next match on grass to Albert Portas,
who was the drop shot dragon.
Am I right, David?
Correct.
I named him that.
That doesn't make Greg look very good, does it?
And then, not long after that,
Vincent Spadia went on an eight-match losing streak.
I sort of wonder, like, how far into that did he start thinking,
oh, not again?
Probably, probably three, I reckon.
Yeah.
Like, but hoping that that doesn't happen to John Schwaard.
So basically there was, there was like a sort of two and a half year period
where Vincent Spadia only beat Greg Rosensky.
That's about the size of it.
Yeah.
McCartney Kessler and Greg Rosensky beat.
Yeah, poor McCartney Kessler.
The Greg Rosensky comparisons.
It's not what you want.
Yeah.
Staying with the women's in Beijing,
Coco Goff and Naomi Osaka is happening.
Finally, we see them on a collision course in a draw
and it's ended up coming off.
Both of them playing with new coaches,
Naomi Osaka, of course, with Patrick Muratoglu in tow
and Coco Goff with somebody who I didn't really know,
Matt Daly has joined her coaching team.
She says, I'm really excited.
These quotes given to the WTA Insider.
I think this is probably what it will look like next year too.
I'm super excited for a new change
and hopefully to improve other parts of my game.
I think it's just time to do a reset, a refresh
and add things in my game that I felt like I need to do
to have a better season next year.
Now, I understand that he has a particular focus on grip changes.
Those are reports that I've read.
Some people speculating that she, well, actually,
I think she's kind of said that she's already made some minor adjustments
and she's played really well.
I watched her beat Katie Bolter yesterday.
Now, I do think that's, I know Bolter's beaten her once before,
but I do think that's a good matchup for Coco Goff,
provided she's playing well.
She can just make Bolter kind of have to win the point over and over and over again
to the point where it kind of malfunctions.
But I've been impressed with her this week
and Naomi Osaka is, she's playing with conviction, isn't she?
She's stepping into the court and just beasting the tennis ball
and kind of bullying opponents in the way that she used to in her heyday.
Now, it's early stages for both of them
and it could just be new manager bounce.
But I am excited for this match, David.
Oh, absolutely.
I think that they showed signs.
I mean, it's four or five years ago now, isn't it?
They showed signs of what a good rivalry they could have.
And, you know, probably at the stage of the career that Osaka's had,
I don't know how long she wants to play for.
But there's still plenty of time
and this is what could be the first installment of many.
And it is interesting seeing players who've already scaled the mountain
and for differing reasons in their two cases
are having to rebuild and come back and now clash again.
And it's going to be very interesting.
Yeah.
I think the most significant thing for Osaka this week
was her win over Putin's saver.
It was the first time she'd won a match from a set down
since March of 2022.
Now, I know she's obviously, you know, had a baby
and been inactive in that time.
But still, it was 22 losses in a row from a set down.
And I've watched a lot of Osaka matches this year.
And yeah, as soon as she's lost that first set,
there have been examples of, you know,
the shoulders slumping a little bit
or the game getting a bit ragged
and it feeling over.
And she dug in extremely well in this match,
which was impressive.
I think it's only the second time all season
that she's managed to win three matches in a row.
And honestly, this is kind of what I expected.
You know, I thought anyway,
like Osaka would have a chance to build during the swing
where she was going to be extremely motivated
at a time of year
where maybe people are a little bit jaded
on hard courts.
You know, like it was all set up for her
to maybe try and make some progress
during this time of year.
And then she brings in the new coach.
And we've seen Muratoglu have an immediate impact
with players in the past.
He certainly had it with Simona Halep.
He's had it with Holger Runo as well.
I think we're maybe a little bit more worried
about the long-term implications of that partnership.
But sort of like as an initial jolt,
I thought it probably would bring some results.
And obviously, you know,
Osaka's the one doing the work on the court
and has played extremely impressively.
And I really don't know which way that match is going to go
because their matches in the past
have been kind of one-sided for both players.
They've both had one-sided wins against each other.
I think if Goff is...
If Goff is...
I think Goff just needed a change, didn't she?
She just needed a break.
And it's not been enough time,
even if she has made some small grip change,
it's not been enough time to overhaul her entire game.
Like, those vulnerabilities are still going to be there.
But I think if she's back in her right, proper mindset
of being able to just come through matches
and compete so incredibly well,
then you'd probably just give her the edge.
But when Osaka's playing as well as she can,
matches feel like they're on her racket as well.
So, yeah, like, can't wait to watch it.
We've been denied it, haven't we?
We've been so close to that match so many times.
We really have.
Yeah, it's been owed by tennis.
So, thank you, tennis gods.
The Beijing WTA event is going to finish
by the time we come back on Thursday,
but that match will have happened.
So, we'll talk about that,
everything else that's happened in the Beijing WTA event
and the men's events in Beijing and Tokyo,
which will have finished by that point.
So, we'll be back on Thursday.
Before then, we have our rescheduled live show
for friends this Wednesday night.
We had to postpone last week due to illness.
Matt is now back to full fitness.
I'm looking at his refreshed face now
and can confirm we're all ready
and raring to go for Wednesday night.
It is a Q&A show with questions from the barge
about coaching, which feels extremely pertinent just now.
We've had some brilliant questions in
and a minor spoiler alert here.
David has been dialing a Dan.
So, that's going to be a great show.
And a Delgado.
A Dan and a Delgado
and I'm sure there'll be some Pam as well.
So, people have been dialed
and some of them rhyme with Dan.
So, if you'd like to join us for that show,
either live or as a podcast,
then become a friend if you aren't already.
And as I say, the link to do that is in our show notes.
We have a mascot for this episode
and frankly, everything up until this point
has just been padding for me to get to Arrow.
Arrow.
I've already sent a picture of Arrow to my mum this morning
when I was going through the agenda.
Arrow is honestly ridiculous.
Probably, and Billie Jean is within it,
in short,
probably one of the most beautiful dogs I've ever seen.
Elizabeth is Arrow's owner
and Elizabeth writes,
Arrow is my sister.
Oh no, so Elizabeth isn't Arrow's owner.
Arrow is my sister and dog,
aka my new niece.
Arrow was adopted in 2023
and is named after one of Anne's favourite
Harry Nielsen songs.
Arrow likes hiking,
wrestling with other dogs,
eating butter off her Grammy's kitchen table
and napping on the coldest bathroom tiles she can find.
She doesn't know much about the rules of tennis
but enjoys the balls immensely.
Now, Elizabeth doesn't tell us what breed Arrow is.
I think that's an Australian shepherd.
But I will put a picture of Arrow on our Instagram
and I invite your feedback on that.
And Elizabeth, please let us know.
I feel quite confident that's an Australian shepherd
but I'm so dazzled by his beauty
that I could be wrong.
He's looking,
he's staring into my soul.
I'm losing concentration.
So thank you, Elizabeth.
And thank you, Arrow.
Hello to our mascots,
the dearly departed Darwin,
Francis and Haida and Soma.
Hello to Billie Jean King and Alana Kloss
who, of course, are sponsors of Billie Jean Canine.
Hello to our top folks and executive producers,
Chris, Greg, Jamie and Jeff.
And Matt, we have some shout-outs.
We have Deborah Bloom.
Hello, Deborah.
Like Gilad Bloom.
Yes.
Yes, a player that we were both on the Champions Tour with briefly.
Yeah, that's right.
Briefly.
Yes.
I knew Gilad Bloom
because there was a Champions Tour event in Sao Paulo
that was held at a tennis club
in the Jewish quarter of Sao Paulo
and the organisers of the tennis club
wanted a Jewish player to compete
and Gilad Bloom was available.
And I played football against Gilad
in the Maradona match, would you believe?
And I've just fact-checked this
by looking above my TV
where the two teams are intermingled
and there is Thomas Muster,
there is Goran Ivenicevic,
there is Diego Maradona,
Davos Shuka, Gilad Bloom and me
and Boris Becker as referee.
So it's between you and Gilad Bloom
for least famous.
Yes.
I will take a photo of the photo for you.
How about that?
What do we know about Deborah?
Deborah is from Indiana.
Oh.
And she's on the barge.
I think the capital of Indiana is Springfield.
No, Springfield, Illinois.
Capital of Indiana.
What else do we know?
Indiana.
Well, Deborah is from a place called
Goshen?
I'm not quite sure how to pronounce that.
Like Deborah Jevons,
the chair of the All England Tennis Club.
Very good.
Indianapolis, of course,
is the capital of Indiana.
I was going to say that
and I thought,
isn't that too obvious?
Sigh.
Deborah, thank you.
I enjoyed that shout out very much.
We've also got James Lynn,
who is from Rye, New York.
Hi, James.
Hello, James.
Presumably New York State
rather than New York City.
Yes.
Um, yeah.
Um, James.
Well, James would like to dedicate
his shout out to his 95-year-old
great uncle, Ken Yang,
who helped raise him
and introduced him to tennis.
Oh, that's magnificent.
Hello, Ken.
Uh, like Ken Rosewall.
What a brilliant
tennis name.
What a brilliant sort of
elder statesman
of tennis name
Ken is.
That is lovely, James.
Hello to you
and hello to
Ken.
And James says
he appreciates the podcast
because we're sports
podcasters
who do not
yell and scream
at each other.
Maybe we should start?
Well, that's what our mate Dave
wants us to do more of,
isn't it?
Yeah.
We'll certainly disagree
but maybe not yell and scream.
Yeah.
No, I'm not sure we'll ever.
We're too...
We're not yell and screamy people.
We're conflict-avoidant Brits,
James.
That's not really our vibe.
Thank you, James.
And finally,
we have Andy Brown
in Orpington, London
but grew up in Reading.
Hey!
Is Andy a Reading fan?
Andy says...
Is he in the depths of despair?
Andy says,
Catherine will sympathise
as I'm a long-standing
Reading fan.
You got a win
at the weekend,
didn't you?
Yeah.
Yeah, we did.
Doesn't mean much
if you cease to exist
but yeah.
And Andy
like Andy Murray
and Andy Roddick
so it's all coming up Andy.
And Andy Carroll
briefly played for Reading.
Now playing somewhere
in France,
I think.
Andy Carroll
when he played for Reading
scored
I think the best goal
to ever be disallowed.
It was against Fulham.
Oh yes,
I agree.
You know that Andy Carroll
is still thinking about that
every night.
That's why he keeps still playing.
He's trying to
one-up it.
He was a good man
for us.
He paid
he played for not very much
to, I mean,
you know,
for selfish reasons
but he,
you know,
he did us a favour
in a dark time
and we are still
in that dark time.
Andy,
you have
my deepest
sympathies
and
yeah,
we're in this together.
So,
thank you very much.
Thank you to all of us.
Shout out friends,
our intro friends,
our friends of the Tennis Podcast.
We will see
lots of you
on Wednesday,
I hope,
8pm UK time.
We'll be live on YouTube
with that coaching show.
It'll also be available
as a podcast
for all friends
of the pod
to listen to.
We'll be back
with a second
main show
this week
on Thursday
and we will speak
to you then.
What a summer of sports.
And now,
it's time
for the ultimate race day.
Kipco British Champions Day
at Ascot Racecourse.
See the sport's
top styles in action
as champions are crowned
at the thrilling
flat season finale.
Bring your friends
and enjoy
the ultimate after party
with a DJ set
from Hot Chip.
Kipco British Champions Day
on Saturday
the 19th of October.
Tickets are selling fast.
Book yours
for just £32
at BritishChampionsDay.com
Look at you
with your fancy pants job
sitting at your laptop
all day
on your video meetings
saying things like
let's circle back
on this
or
can you drill down
on that
or
deep dive.
You know what you are
don't you?
You're entitled
that's what.
That's right
most people
who use a screen
at work
are entitled
to claim free eye care.
Ask your boss
about getting
one of our vouchers.
Should have
reached out
to Specsavers.
Specsavers.
.