Welcome to the Tech Meme Right Home for Thursday, October 10th, 2024. I'm Brian McCullough. Today,
Apple TV Plus finally comes to prime video channels. OpenAI says they've been disrupting
AI election influence campaigns, but they won't be profitable until when? How Google plans to
beat the regulation rap and a review of basically the highest-end smartwatch you can buy. Here's
what you missed today in the world of tech.
Amazon has announced that Apple TV Plus will soon be available as a $9.99 per month subscription
add-on in Prime video channels. That's coming later this month in the U.S., joining more than
100 streaming services already there, quoting Bloomberg. What we offer channel partners is
hundreds of millions of subscribers around the world. Amazon said having this engagement around
the world with Prime members, accessing Prime video is a real great platform for other partners to be
able to reach them, end quote. Amazon markets more than 100 streaming services via its channel's store,
enabling customers to watch shows from Max, Paramount Plus, and Hallmark within Prime video.
Those services rely on Amazon to expand their audience. Apple TV Plus was one of the only major
streaming services not available in the store, along with Netflix and Walt Disney's main properties.
Those two are among the few with streaming services that have more viewers than Prime video.
The agreement expands an existing relationship between the companies. In 2017, Amazon started
offering a Prime video app on the Apple TV set-top box, while Prime video is integrated into the Apple
TV app across the iPhone maker's device lineup. The two companies are also retail partners with Apple
offering an official store via Amazon.com, end quote.
OpenAI says it has disrupted more than 20 operations and deceptive networks so far this year that tried
to use its models for disinformation purposes, including four that had election-related content,
quoting CNBC. In a 54-page report published Wednesday, the chat GPT creator said that it's
disrupted, quote, more than 20 operations and deceptive networks from around the world
that attempted to use our models. The threats ranged from AI-generated website articles to social media
posts by fake accounts. The company said its update on influence and cyber operations was intended to
provide a snapshot of what it's seeing and to identify, quote, an initial set of trends that we believe
can inform debate on how AI fits into the broader threat landscape, end quote.
OpenAI's report lands less than a month before the U.S. presidential election, but beyond the U.S.,
it's a significant year for elections worldwide, with contests taking place that affect upward of 4
billion people in more than 40 countries. The rise of AI-generated content has led to serious
election-related misinformation concerns, with the number of deepfakes that have been created
increasing 900% year over year, according to data from Clarity, a machine learning firm.
OpenAI wrote in its report that election-related uses of AI, quote,
ranged in complexity from simple requests for content generation to complex multi-stage efforts
to analyze and reply to social media posts. The social media content related mostly to elections
in the U.S. and Rwanda, and to a lesser extent, elections in India and the EU, OpenAI said.
In late August, an Iranian operation used OpenAI's products to generate, quote,
long-form articles and social media comments about the U.S. election, as well as other topics,
but the company said the majority of identified posts received few or no likes, shares, or comments.
In July, the company banned ChatGPT accounts in Rwanda that were posting election-related comments
on X, and in May, an Israeli company used ChatGPT to generate social media comments about elections
in India. OpenAI wrote that it was able to address the case within less than 24 hours.
In June, OpenAI addressed a covert operation that used its products to generate comments about the
European Parliament elections in France and politics in the U.S., Germany, Italy, and Poland.
The company said that while most social media posts it identified received few likes or shares,
some real people did reply to the AI-generated posts. None of the election-related operations
were able to attract viral engagement or build sustained audiences via the use of ChatGPT
and OpenAI's other tools the company wrote, end quote.
Sticking with OpenAI for one more second, the information has seen internal documents from
OpenAI with projections suggesting that the company won't turn a profit until 2029 when its revenue
would hit $100 billion. Losses could hit $14 billion in 2026, up nearly 3x on this year.
So if true, number one, they need to hit $100 billion in revenue just to turn a profit. That
does suggest that margins aren't great. But number two, that level of cash burn suggests they have
a hell of a needle to thread. Quote,
This estimate doesn't include stock compensation, which is one of OpenAI's biggest expenses,
although not one it pays in cash. OpenAI is emphasizing to investors a metric of profitability
that excludes some major expenses, such as the billions it is spending annually on training its
large language models. The documents show, by that metric, OpenAI projects it will turn
profitable in 2026. The company last week completed a $6.6 billion funding round, valuing it at $157
billion. The documents, which include financial statements and forecasts, contain a number of
revelations about OpenAI that may change perceptions of the company's financial prospects.
OpenAI appears to be burning far less cash than previously thought. The company burned through
about $340 million in the first half of this year, leaving it with $1 billion in cash on the
balance sheet before the fundraising effort. But the cash burn could accelerate sharply in the next
couple of years, the documents suggest. There's a big gap between OpenAI's cash flow and its bottom
line, reflecting standard accounting differences in how it treats its major expenses, such as stock
compensation and compute credits in different financial statements. OpenAI calculated its net loss to be
$3 billion for the first half of the year. OpenAI expects to spend more than $200 billion through
the end of the decade, excluding stock compensation costs. Between 60 to 80% of its spending each year
would go toward either training or running the models. An analysis of the documents suggests that
OpenAI projects its total losses between 2023 and 2028, excluding stock compensation, will be $44 billion.
The same analysis suggests the company anticipates it will make $14 billion in profit on that basis in
2029. In the first half of this year, the company reported stock compensation of $1.5 billion, likely
equivalent to its revenue in the period. The documents imply that Microsoft gets a cut of 20% of OpenAI's
revenues, which is higher than previously thought. OpenAI is projecting that computing costs for model
training could rise sharply in the next couple of years to as high as $9.5 billion a year
in 2026. That's in addition to the amortized upfront costs of training for large language model research,
which its financial documents report as research compute costs spread out over a number of years.
That figure is also rising sharply to more than $5 billion in 2026 from a projected $1 billion this year.
Some of OpenAI's computing costs aren't paid in cash. Microsoft advanced OpenAI computing credits as part
of its $10 billion investment last year. And in the first half of this year, OpenAI recorded about
$500 million of data center lease expenses covered by Microsoft, according to the documents and a
person familiar with the matter. It's unclear how many computing credits OpenAI has left. It's likely,
however, that OpenAI will have to spend more of its own cash if it increases compute spending as much
as projected in the documents. OpenAI also has been discussing borrowing money to try to set up data
centers more quickly than Microsoft can, the information reported this week. Still, OpenAI could scale back
the compute spending, for instance, if upcoming models have more staying power than prior ones because
rivals aren't able to catch up quickly, or if the models are less costly to train because of future
breakthroughs. That would reduce the demands on its cash resources."
This makes me a tiny bit concerned about the Vision Pro. Sources say Dan Riccio, Apple's Vision Pro
chief and former senior vice president of hardware engineering is leaving Apple in October. The
Vision Pro team will now report to John Ternus, quoting Bloomberg.
Mike Rockwell, Riccio's current lieutenant, will continue to lead the Vision products group on a
day-to-day basis, said the people who asked not to be identified because the changes aren't public.
A spokesperson for the Cupertino, California-based company declined to comment.
Riccio's exit marks one of the most significant departures from Apple's management team,
though it's been in the making for some time. Three years ago, he switched from being a senior
vice president to a vice president and left the 12-person executive team a step toward his
eventual retirement. Riccio spoke at an event at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology on Wednesday,
telling students he is winding down his career at Apple. He said he wants to get more involved at
the engineering program named for him at the university, including by potentially teaching or
developing curriculum material. He also spoke about the birth of the original iMac and said the
iPhone X was the product he was most proud to create. The executive spent 26 years at the
company and was known at times for an abrasive style and controversial moves, but he also made
key hires and encouraged acquisitions that resulted in major new products. His tenure included overseeing
some of Apple's biggest bets, including development of the Vision Pro headset and the failed bid to make
a car." There's no shortage of helpful AI tools out there, but using them means switching back and
forth between yet another digital tool. So instead of simplifying your workflow, it just becomes more
complicated. Unless, of course, you're in Notion. The new Notion AI is a single AI tool that does it all.
You can search across Notion and other apps, generate docs in your own style, analyze PDFs and images,
and it will chat with you about anything. Notion AI is connected to multiple knowledge sources. It uses
AI knowledge from GPT-4 and Claude to chat with you about any topic. It can search across thousands of
Notion docs in seconds to quickly answer any question. And with AI connectors now in beta,
Notion AI can search across Slack, discussions, Google Docs, sheets, and slides,
and more tools like GitHub and Jira are coming soon. Unlike other specialized tools or legacy
suites that have you bouncing between six different apps, Notion is seamlessly integrated,
infinitely flexible, and beautifully easy to use. Try Notion for free when you go to
notion.com slash ride. That's all lowercase letters, notion.com slash ride to try the powerful,
easy-to-use Notion AI today. And when you use our link, you're supporting our show, notion.com slash ride.
How do you make a password that's strong enough no one will be able to guess it, but also impossible
to forget? And how can you do that for a hundred different websites? And how can you make it so
everyone in your company can do the same without ever having the need to reset them? Sounds like
an impossible task unless you have 1Password. As I've said, I've been using 1Password for about 15 years.
I have it on every computer and phone I've had over that time. I used 1Password today. I used it like
three minutes ago. Companies lose hours every day just from employees forgetting and resetting passwords.
A single data breach costs millions of dollars, but 1Password secures every sign-in to save you time and money.
Any device, any time. 1Password lets you securely switch between iPhone, Android, Mac, and PC with
convenient features like Autofill for quick sign-ins. All you have to do is remember the one strong
account password that protects everything else. Your logins, your credit cards, secure notes,
or the office Wi-Fi password. Protect your global workforce with simple security, easy secret
sharing, and actionable insight reports. Right now, my listeners get a free two-week trial at
1password.com slash ride for your growing business. That's two free weeks at 1password.com slash ride.
Don't let security slow your business down. Go to 1password.com slash ride.
The Financial Times takes a look at how Google plans to deflect and delay that U.S. breakup threat
that we spoke about yesterday. A Remedies ruling is likely in mid-2025, but legal timelines may let it
put off any impact of that ruling for years. Quote, Google's initial response to the DOJ's proposals
that competition is thriving in search ads and fierce in artificial intelligence would have been less
convincing even two years ago before OpenAI's launch of the breakthrough chat GPT chatbot. Spinning out
its arguments through the appeals courts will be crucial to Google's strategy as it looks to deflect
or delay the effects of August's landmark ruling by a federal judge that it maintained an illegal
monopoly by paying billions of dollars to device makers, mobile carriers, and browser developers.
The legal timelines involved in such a complex and high-stakes case are likely to allow Google to put
off any impact on its business for years. It plans to appeal the liability decision when the judge rules
on remedies, which is likely to be in mid-2025, and may then also contest the remedies themselves.
Broadly, Google's argument focuses on what it describes as regulatory overreach following a case
about the impact of its distribution agreements. Forcing it to divest assets or share data with
competitors would, quote, go far beyond the specific legal issues in this case, it said in a blog post on
Tuesday. Requiring Google to split off its Chrome browser or Android operating system or other
structural remedies would, quote, tilt the field at the precise moment that competition is thriving,
the company said. With new search advertising competitors such as Amazon and TikTok emerging
and widespread disruption to its core business from AI startups, including OpenAI and perplexity,
Google can argue that it is facing the stiffest competition since Microsoft's Bing launched 15 years ago.
On Tuesday, for example, Google pointed to an e-marketer forecast that its share of U.S. search
advertising spending would fall below 50% next year for the first time since the research group started
tracking the market in 2008, primarily due to rapid growth in Amazon's marketing business.
The company is likely to appeal its antitrust cases all the way up to the U.S. Supreme Court.
This is the start of a long process, it said in Tuesday's blog post.
Yet Jason Kent, a big tech critic who leads the digital content Next trade group of online publishers,
said it was not a given that the Supreme Court would take up the case. He estimated that it could
take two or three years for any remedies to be enforced if the case proceeds through the courts,
adding, quote, the reality is Google is racking up legal losses, they have a difficult set of facts
along with spoliation from purging evidence, and they may try to settle or proactively make moves
to control the outcome, end quote. Finally today, a review. The Verge says that the Garmin
Phoenix 8, the $1,000 smartwatch, has excellent battery life and fitness tracking and an OLED display,
but it costs $350 more than the Phoenix 7 and lacks LTE, which apparently is key, quote.
The big additions to the Phoenix 8 are a speaker and microphone. They mean you can now interact
with the watch in more ways than fitness tracking and training. You can take calls from the wrist,
use an on-device voice assistant for setting timers and starting activities,
and connect to your phone's built-in assistant for more complex queries. If you can convince your
loved ones to download the new Garmin Messenger app, replying to messages on the wrist also has gotten
easier. Theoretically, these are all good updates. In practice, it means the Phoenix 8 doesn't play to
Garmin's strengths. The bulk of the smart updates zero in on the addition of the microphone and speaker,
namely voice assistants and calling from the wrist. But there's a big factor holding back the Phoenix
8's smart features, the lack of LTE. Yes, you can make and receive calls with the Phoenix 8 so long as
your phone is within Bluetooth range. Yes, you can talk to a voice assistant, but it's limited unless
your phone is nearby. Yes, you can reply to text, but you get my drift. If you get a cellular Apple Watch,
Galaxy Watch, or Pixel Watch, you can leave your phone at home. That's not really an option with
the Phoenix 8. The friction is particularly noticeable with the on-device voice assistant.
The assistant works pretty well, but it's mostly limited to commands that don't require an internet
connection. You can start activities, set timers, and tweak settings. It can tell you the weather,
provided it's loaded the day's weather from Wi-Fi or your phone via Bluetooth. But say you want to send
a text message. This nameless assistant can't do that. Instead, you'll have to scroll to a different menu
and launch your phone's assistant. It's good to have that option, but at that point, you're probably
just going to whip out your phone anyway. Part of the problem is that Garmin has always been staunchly
platform agnostic. I happen to think that's a good thing, but the price you pay is never having your
watch work quite as seamlessly with your phone. For example, it's great that you can dictate voice
memos now, but their usefulness is limited because there's no easy way to get them off your wrist and
onto another device. That's unlike the Pixel Watch 3 where I can just record something and boom,
it's magically on my Pixel 8 Pro. Everyone I've ever met with a Phoenix watch has been a triathlete,
ultramarathoner, or someone who casually qualifies for the Boston Marathon with a sub-three-hour
marathon time. These folks pick something like the Phoenix because they need a tracker with Mondo
battery life, stellar GPS accuracy, in-depth training programs, and maps for traversing trails.
Those are the features that people would leave Apple or Samsung for, and they don't get a major
upgrade with the Phoenix 8. To make matters worse, I almost choked when I saw the Phoenix 8's starting
price was a whole $350 more than the Phoenix 7. That's not a $50 to $100 hike where you grumble
and then begrudgingly admit that inflation is a bitch. For $999, you could buy a laptop. Hell,
the Apple Watch Ultra 2 is $800 while the Galaxy Watch Ultra is $650. Those do come with LTE,
and if you're determined to get a Garmin, there are literally dozens of cheaper options. Might I
suggest the $450 Forerunner, 265, or a discounted Phoenix 7 Pro or Epix Pro? It's frustrating because
Garmin is right to shore up its smart features. There's not much to improve on the fitness front,
so making its watches more useful outside of training makes a lot of sense. It's also crystal
clear that Garmin has some catching up to do, and progress isn't going to happen overnight.
The Phoenix 8 might be on the right track, but it doesn't quite nail the price or execution.
End quote.
Okay, everybody. Rad 80s, 90s history is currently number 34 on the history chart. Please, if you
haven't done so, subscribe to the show. Especially if you use Apple Podcasts, please follow the show
on Apple Podcasts. And also, write a review. Give it five stars and write a quick sentence or two
review. Even if you've already subscribed, go back and do that. It'll really help. We can do this,
people. We can get to number one. The history category is not as competitive as some others,
so we can make my dream come true of having a number one podcast. Link in the show notes to the
Apple Podcasts link itself. Again, please follow, rate, and review. Thanks in advance.